A Guide to the Papers of William Faulkner and the Faulkner Family, 1926-1992
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
A Guide to the Papers of William Faulkner and the Faulkner Family 1926-1992
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
9817-m
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These papers were loaned to the University of Virginia Library by Jill Faulkner Summers on November 1, 2000.
Scope and Content
This addition to the papers of William Faulkner, ca. 1926-1992, ca. 195 items (4 Hollinger boxes, ca. 2 linear feet), consists of business, personal and legal correspondence and documents of Faulkner and family members Jill Faulkner Summers and Malcolm Argyle Franklin. The papers consist of business, personal and legal correspondence and documents of Faulkner and family members Jill Faulkner Summers and Malcolm Franklin. The papers also contain several miscellaneous legal papers, including a deed for Rowan Oak to Jill Faulkner Summers.
Memorabilia from a scrapbook compiled by Jill Faulkner Summers includes a dress pattern, invitations, dance cards, clippings, receipts, horse show programs, sketches, a story, academic notes, exam answer sheets, and letters written as a child to relatives including one mentioning riding with Deanna Durbin.
Papers pertaining to Malcolm Franklin include a class notebook in parasitology, 1949, and various other medical pamphlets, together with World War II letters to his family from Camp Joseph T. Robinson and Germany and photographs of Franklin and Victoria Franklin.
A small group of papers concern W. F. Fielden and the Proctor and Gamble Defense Corporation, chiefly issues of the Wolf Creek Banner, 1944-1945.
There is also an unmarked phonodisk with unidentified content.
Arrangement
This addition to the papers of William Faulkner consists of four series: Series I: Harold Ober Associates Material; Subseries A: Work by William Faulkner; Subseries B: Work concerning William Faulkner; Series II: William Faulkner and Jill Faulkner Summers Material; Subseries A: Contracts and Agreements; Subseries B: Manuscripts by William Faulkner (alphabetical); Subseries C: Printed Material concerning William Faulkner (chronological); Subseries D: Personal Notebook, etc.; Series III: Malcolm Franklin Papers; Series IV: William F. Fielden and Proctor and Gamble Defense Corporation
Contents List
- Series I: Harold Ober Associates Material
  - Subseries A: Work by William Faulkner
    - Almost, n.d., TMs. (Box-folder 1:1)
      22 pages.
    - An Innocent at Rinkside, n.d., TMs (carbon). (Box-folder 1:2)
      5 pages.
    - The Bear, 1942, TMs (carbon). (Box-folder 1:3)
      20 pages.
    - A Courtship, Sewanee Review, 1948, Galley Proof. (Box-folder 1:4)
      6 pages.
    - By the People, Mademoiselle, 1955 October, Printed. (Box-folder 1:5)
      14 pages.
    - Freedom American Style, 1955, TMs (carbon). (Box-folder 1:6)
      16 pages.
    - Hog Pawn, n.d., TMs. (Box-folder 1:7)
      28 pages.
    - Knight's Gambit, [photocopy only], little story in book of the same name, n.d., TMs. (Box-folder 1:8)
    - Letter to a Northern Editor, n.d., TMs (carbon). (Box-folder 1:9)
      7 pages.
    - Lucas Beauchamp, n.d., TMs. (Box-folder 1:10)
      26 pages.
    - Mississippi, n.d., TMs. (Box-folder 1:11)
      38 pages.
    - On Fear, The South in Labor: Mississippi, n.d., TMs (carbon). (Box-folder 1:12)
      17 pages (2 copies).
    - On Privacy (The American Dream: What Happened to It?), formerly entitled Freedom American Style, n.d., TMs (carbon). (Box-folder 1:13)
    - Race at Morning, Saturday Evening Post tearsheets, 4 pages, n.d., Printed. (Oversize OS Box P-26.)
    - Requiem for a Nun, fully cut script, ca. 70 pages, 1958, Script. (Box-folder 1:14)
    - Requiem for a Nun, fully cut script, property of Zachary Scott, 1958, ca. 70 pages. (Box-folder 1:15)
      Script.
    - Sherwood Anderson: An Appreciation by William Faulkner, The Atlantic tearsheets, 1953 June, Printed. 3 pages, 5 copies. (Oversize OS Box P-26)
    - Smoke, Ellery Queen's Mystery Magazine, 1947 October, Printed. (Box-folder 1:16)
      23 pages.
    - Speech at National Book Awards Meeting, 1955, TMs. (Box-folder 1:17)
      3 pages.
    - Speech at National Book Awards Meeting, New York Times Review, 1955, Printed. (Box-folder 1:18)
      2 pages.
    - Three Days Before, n.d., TMs. (Box-folder 1:19)
    - Thrift, Saturday Evening Post tearsheets, 1930 September, Printed. 5 pages. (Oversize OS Box P-26.)
    - Two Soldiers, Saturday Evening Post, 1942 March, Printed. (Oversize OS Box P-26.)
    - Weekend Revisited, n.d., TMs (carbon). 20 pages. (Box-folder 1:20)
    - William Faulkner on Dialect, ed. by Frederick L. Gwynn and Joseph L. Botner, The University of Virginia Magazine, 1958 Winter, Printed. (Box-folder 1:21)
    - A Word to Virginians, with autograph revisions in unidentified hand, 1958, TMs. (Box-folder 1:22)
      4 pages.
    - A Word to Virginians, 1958, TMs (carbons). (Box-folder 1:23)
      6 pages (2 copies).
    - A Word to Young Writers Delivered to University of Virginia English Club, 1958, TMs. (Box-folder 1:24)
      7 pages (3 copies).
  - Subseries B: Work concerning William Faulkner
    - Afternoon of a Cow, by Ernest V. Trueblood, Furioso tearsheets, 1947 Summer, Printed. 25 pages. (Box-folder 1:25)
    - The Art of Fiction: An Interview with Faulkner- September 1955, by Cynthia Grenier, Accent, 1956 Summer, Printed. 11 pages. (Box-folder 1:26)
    - The Art of Fiction XII: William Faulkner, interview by Jean Stein, Paris Review #12, 1956 Spring, Printed. 25 pages (2 copies). (Box-folder 1:27)
    - Faulkner in Japan: Interview with and Impressions by William Faulkner, Esquire, 1958 December, Printed. 4 pages. (Oversize OS Box P-26.)
    - Faulkner in the University: A Classroom Conference, ed. by Frederick L. Gwynn and Joseph Botner, College English, 1957 October, Printed. 6 pages. (Box-folder 1:28)
    - Faulkner Studies, Volume II, Nos. 1 and 2, 1953, Printed. (Box-folder 1:29)
    - Interview with William Faulkner, by Jean Stein, 1956 May, TMs. (Box-folder 1:30)
      35 pages.
    - Joe Christmas: The Hero in the Modern World, by John L. Longley, Jr., Virginia Quarterly Review, 1957 Spring, Printed. 15 pages. (Box-folder 1:31)
    - Les Aventures du reve American par William Faulkner, L'Express, 1955 September, Printed. (Oversize OS Box P-26.)
    - Maria, Deux Actes d'Andre Obey inspriree d'une nouvelle de William Faulkner [Maria, by Andre Obey inspired by a novel of William Faulkner], n.d., Script. 74 pages. (Box-folder 1:32)
    - Requiem pour une Nonne, Program for Theatre Marcel Herrand- Albert Camus' dramatization, Saison, France, 1956-1957, Printed. (Box-folder 1:33)
    - Sepulture South: Gaslight, Harper's Bazaar tearsheets, 1954 December, Printed. 3 pages. (Oversize OS Box P-26.)
- Series II: William Faulkner and Jill Faulkner Summers Material
  - Subseries A: Contracts and Agreements
    - Contracts and Agreements, 1954-1971, 8 items. (Box-folder 2:1)
      Includes:
      a)Warranty deed to Jill Faulkner for Rowan Oak (June 20, 1954)
      b) Quit claim deed from Jill Faulkner Summers to William Faulkner and Estelle Oldham Faulkner (March 21, 1955) correcting an inadvertent error in the June 20, 1954 deed
      c) Deed of gift from William Faulkner and Estelle Oldham Faulkner to Jill Faulkner Summers conveying title to Rowan Oak (July 21, 1960)
      d) Rider to Stock Try-Out Contract on As I Lay Dying between William Faulkner and Baylor University (January 8, 1960)
      e) Lomax B. Lamb, Jr. Law Offices, Marks, Mississippi, to Paul Summers, Charlottesville, regarding a Museum in Oxford and its director (July 10, 1963)
      f) Lomax B. Lamb, Jr. to Mr. and Mrs. Paul D. Summers, carbon of letter sent to Mrs. William Faulkner, Charlottesville, with letter from Mrs. Herron Rowland, Director of the Mary Buie Museum, Oxford, Mississippi, and an acknowledgment and listing of materials on exhibit at the Museum in a display case designated The William Faulkner Case, loaned to the Museum by William Faulkner and family (August 9, 1963)
      g) James W. Webb, Chairman, Department of English, University of Mississippi, to Mrs. Paul Summers, Charlottesville, August 5, 1964, with carbon letter, April 9, 1965, Webb to Lamb, concerning the retirement of Mrs. Herron Rowland and the understanding that the Faulkner awards would be moved to the Mississippi Room at the University following her retirement
      h) Promissory note to the order of Random House, Inc. from Jill Faulkner Summers (March 9, 1971); cancelled by payment January 15, 1980
  - Subseries B: Manuscripts by William Faulkner (alphabetical)
    - Grandfather Said, with autograph revisions by Faulkner, 1962, TMs. 3 pages. (Box-folder 2:2)
    - Grandfather Said, with autograph revision in unknown hand, 1962, TMs (carbon). 22 pages. (Box-folder 2:3)
    - Hells Creek Crossing, tearsheets, 1962 September, Printed. 4 pages. (Oversize OS Box P-26.)
    - Mr. Acarius, tearsheets, 1965, Printed. 16 pages. (Oversize OS Box P-26.)
    - Untitled Piece about Albert Camus, 1960, TMs. (Box-folder 2:4)
      With autograph note at top and revisions by Faulkner, 2 pages.
    - Untitled Piece about Albert Camus, 1960, TMs (carbon). 2 pages (2 copies). (Box-folder 2:5)
  - Subseries C: Printed Material concerning William Faulkner (chronological)
    - Time cover of William Faulkner; Books: The Wild Palms review When the Dam Breaks, pages 45-46, 1939, Printed. 3 copies. (Box-folder 2:6)
    - Time, including: Books: Intruder in the Dust review, October 4, 1948, page 108 and People- The Laurels, December 6, 1948, page 42, 1948, Printed. (Box-folder 2:7)
    - Three Nobel Prize Winners, by Dan Gable, Sigma Alpha Epsilon, 1951 February, Printed. 3 pages. (Box-folder 2:8)
    - Time, Books: Requiem for a Nun review, pages 114-117, 1951 September 24, Printed. (Box-folder 2:9)
    - Le premier chapitre du dernier roman de William Faulkner 'L 'Intrus das la poussiere,' Vogue (Paris), 1952 February, Printed. 3 pages. (Oversize OS Box P-26.)
    - Final Fanfare for '53, Life, page 25, 1953 June, Printed. (Oversize OS Box P-26.)
    - Untitled Piece, by Jill Faulkner Summers, 1958, TMs. 8 pages. (Box-folder 2:10)
    - La Nouvelle Revue Francaise Hommage a Albert Camus 1913-1960, 1960, Page Proof. (Box-folder 2:11)
    - Time, Books: The Reivers review, page 92, 1962 June 8, Printed. (Box-folder 2:12)
    - Building Blocks of a Gentleman, by Granville Hicks, Saturday Review, page 27, 1962 June, Printed. (Box-folder 2:13)
    - The Reivers review, Picaresque and Puzzling, Newsweek tearsheet, 1962 June, Printed. 1 page. (Box-folder 2:14)
    - William Faulkner: Man and Writer, Hamilton Basso, Saturday Review, 1962 July, Printed. 3 copies. (Box-folder 2:15)
    - William Faulkner 1897-1962, by Fredson Bowers, University of Virginia Topics, 1962 Summer, Printed. (Box-folder 2:16)
    - The Death of William Faulkner, by Hughes Rudd, Saturday Evening Post tearsheets, 1963 July, Printed. 4 pages. (Oversize OS Box P-26.)
    - The Visible Man, by Ralph Ellison, review, Newsweek, page 81, 1963 August, Printed. (Box-folder 2:17)
    - Col. Sartoris and Mr. Snopes, by Nancy Hale, Vogue, 1963 August, Printed. 6 pages. (Oversize OS Box P-26.)
    - Faulkner Country, Life tearsheets, 9 pages, Mississippi Quarterly, 8 pages, 1963 August, Printed. (Oversize OS Box P-26.)
    - Time, 1964 July, Printed. (Box-folder 2:18)
      Includes: July 17, 1964 cover of William Faulkner, and Books: Absalom, Absalom! review, The Curse and the Hope, 5 pages; and July 24, 1964 Letters to the Editor, including one from Bennett Cerf, concerning the previous Faulkner cover story, page 9.
    - Faulkner articles, The Delta Review, 1965, Printed. 7 pages. (Box-folder 2:19)
    - Faulkner's Verbena, by Jane Isbell Haynes, The Mississippi Quarterly, 1980 Summer, Reprint. 8 pages. (Box-folder 2:20)
    - Surveying the South, a panorama-in-print, by Norman Schreiber, Smithsonia, 1989 September, Printed. 2 pages. (Box-folder 2:21)
    - Architecture and the Tangible Past: The Built Environment of Faulkner's Yoknapatawpha, Places: A Quarterly Journal of Environmental Design, 1989, Printed. 16 pages. (Box-folder 2:22)
    - Sanctuary of the Storyteller, Southern Accents, 1992 April, Printed. 10 pages. (Box-folder 2:23)
  - Subseries D: Jill Faulkner Summers Personal Notebook
    - Notebook pertaining to and compiled by Jill Faulkner, 1935-1968, 23 items. (Box-folder 3:1)
      Includes (original order and numbering retained):
      JF 1: Hollywood dress pattern, size 8 years
      JF 2: The American Girl subscription order blank, scribbled
      JF 3: Envelope, return address 1410 N. Brenda St, Hollywood, addressed to Mrs. LE. Oldham, June 27,1944
      JF 4: letter accompanying JF 3, to grandparents and D. Oldham
      JF 5: Envelope, return address 1410 N. Brenda St., Hollywood, addressed to D. Oldham, July 7, 1944
      JF 6: Letter accompanying JF 5, Dear Aunt Dot, details Hollywood experience
      JF 7: Letter, Dear Aunt Dot and Miss Mary, n.d. apparently written after JF 6. Details riding, mentions riding with Deanna Durbin, and mentions other film stars
      JF 8: newspaper clipping of Jean Sullivan selling poppies for war effort, 1945
      JF 9: Homemade dance card, red stock, silver ink, Tea Dance, honoring Miss Jill Faulkner, Tuesday afternoon, December 23, 1947 at Mrs. LE. Oldham's
      JF 10: Homemade dance card, white stock, pasted on magazine pink rose, Dance for Miss Jill Faulkner. Friday evening June 18th, 1948
      JF 11: Duplicate of JF 10, no rose
      JF 12: Duplicate of JF 10, clipped in half
      JF 13: Card, Jill Faulkner, A. A.U.W. award to a Junior High student writing best original poem, (found in Untermeyer, This Singing World: possibly the book was the prize)
      JF 14: Penmanship award, The National Board of Examiners, March 3, 1944 (fifth grade)
      JF 15: Guess I'd better ring for help caption on horse clipping from magazine
      JF 16: My Spelling Book fifth grade, 1944-45
      JF 17: Arithmetic Workbook, third grade. Blue cover, red Binding, tablet style
      JF 18: Birthday telegram to Estelle Faulkner from Wellesley, Massachusetts
      JF 19: Gift card, "My precious Mama Many many happy returns of the day. I love you more than you can ever know. Jill."
      JF 20: Railway Express Agency receipt for baggage shipped to Pine Manor College, November 28, 1951
      JF 21: Railway Express Agency receipt for baggage shipped to Pine Manor college, April 29, 1953
      JF 22: Small watercolor of Mexican peasant, seated with head down
      JF 23: Postcard, Trier, "Just another one for your collection, love, Malcolm."
    - Notebook pertaining to and compiled by Jill Faulkner, 1935-1968, 24 items. (Box-folder 3:2)
      JF 24: Mimeographed legal sized sheet of high school cheers
      JF 25: Manuscript page, Betty Cofield was sixteen...
      JF 26: Childhood triangle sketches
      JF 27: Equestrian supply catalogue, No. 135 English Super Saddlery, The Little Joe Wiesenfeld Co., 112 W. North Avenue, Baltimore, 1947
      JF 28: Souvenir program of Holly Springs, MS, horse show, July 22, 1946
      JF 29: Souvenir program of Holly Springs, MS, horse show, June 13, 1947
      JF 30: Letter from University of Mississippi Student Personnel Department regarding American council Psychological Examination, June 9, 1951
      JF 31: Astronomy study sheet, legal size, folded, probably dated Summer 1951
      JF 32: Physics exam sheet, June 18,1951
      JF 33: History notes, chapter 27
      JF 34: Astronomy notes, steno pad sheet
      JF 35: Letter from UM student personnel, announcement of meeting for all incoming freshmen, June 9, 1951
      JF 36: Physics exam, July 3, 1951
      JF 37: Long envelope, student personnel
      JF 38: Short envelope, student personnel
      JF 39: Wedding invitation, illustrated by Maud Falkner
      JF 40: Wedding invitation
      JF 41: Card for enclosure with invitation for reception at Rowan Oak
      JF 42: Telegram to Paul Summers from Bill Marriott, Athens, Georgia, concerning wedding plans
      JF 43: Full page clipping of Memphis Commercial Appeal coverage of Jill's wedding and reception
      JF 44: Pamphlet, The Man Who Owned the Stable, inscribed, For Paul and Jill, Christmas, 1956
      JF 45: Letter on newsprint quality paper, legal size, to parents, written during first pregnancy, envelope, postmarked November 7, 1955
      JF 46: Assembly instructions for Edison cribs
      JF 47: Letter and envelope to Estelle Faulkner, postmarked Charlottesville, July 24, 1968
    - National Geographic Magazine, 1943 June, Printed. (Box-folder 3:3)
    - Time during World War II, 1945 April-June, Printed. 3 issues. (Box-folder 3:4)
    - Time during World War II, 1945 August-September, Printed. 3 issues. (Box-folder 3:5)
    - The University of the Air: A Decade of Progress, 1951, Printed. (Box-folder 3:6)
    - The Spanish Riding School of Vienna, a gift to Tad Summers from Edna,1969, Printed. (Box-folder 3:7)
    - Page from Scrapbook with Pictures of Estelle Oldham Faulkner and her sister, Dorothy Oldham, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 3:8)
    - Open Thou Mine Eyes, by Dorothy Zolicoffer Oldham, n.d. (Box-folder 3:9)
    - Institutes De Justinien, n.d., Printed. (Box-folder 3:10)
- Series III: Malcolm Franklin Papers
  - Malcolm Argyle Franklin Papers (folder 1 of 7), 1926-1952, 6 items. (Box-folder 4:1)
    Contains pamphlets of anatomy, biology, morphology, physiology, and zoology; an English assignment notebook; a Valentine to Estelle Oldham Faulkner.
  - Malcolm Argyle Franklin Papers (folder 2 of 7), 1926-1952, 7 items. (Box-folder 4:2)
    Contains letters to L.E. Oldham from camp during WWII, discussing learning army methods of laboratory techniques, manuevers, and camp life at Camp Joseph T. Robinson, Arkansas; a sketch of himself.
  - Malcolm Argyle Franklin Papers (folder 3 of 7), 1926-1952, 8 items. (Box-folder 4:3)
    Contains postcards from Germany to Jill Faulkner; a Webster Dictionary; Neuroanatomy report- Neuro-Anatomy Drawings by M.A. Franklin, 1950; Typescript, Opsanus Tau with related forms reported from the Gulf of Mexico.
  - Malcolm Argyle Franklin Papers (folder 4 of 7), 1926-1952, 6 items. (Box-folder 4:4)
    Contains pamphlets on anatomy, biology, morphology, physiology, and zoology.
  - Malcolm Argyle Franklin Papers (Folder 5 of 7), 1926-1952, 10 items. (Box-folder 4:5)
  - Malcolm Argyle Franklin Papers (Folder 6 of 7), containing a Parasitology class notebook, 1926-1952, 1 item. (Box-folder 4:6)
  - Malcolm Argyle Franklin Papers (Folder 7 of 7), 1926-1952, 1 item. (Box-folder 4:7)
    Contains a Perpetual Date Book, with brief personal notes, many of which mention the Faulkners and the Oldhams.
  - Photographs of Malcolm A. Franklin, n.d. (Oversize OS Box Q-17.)
  - Photographs of Victoria Franklin, n.d. (Oversize OS Box Q-17.)
- Series IV: William F. Fielden - Proctor and Gamble Defense Corporation
  - Proctor and Gamble Defense Corporation, 1944-1948, 5 items. (Box-folder 4:8)
    Includes: Program for the Army-Navy E Fourth Annual Dinner (November 16, 1944); Certificate of Award to William F. Fielden, for his part in winning the Army-Navy 'E' Award for Wolf Creek Ordnance Plant, Milan, Tennessee (November 18, 1944); Report, Planning and Operations of Finished Ammunition Stores, W.F. Fielden (December 1944); Certificate of Memberhip, American Junior Chamber of Commerce, Shanghai by W.F. Fielden (May 21, 1948).
  - Proctor and Gamble Defense Corporation: Editions of Wolf Creek Banner and Newspaper Clippings, 1944-1945, 12 items. (Box-folder 4:9)